{
  "reference_number": "8605",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "It is important to set a firm goal immediately and begin work on emissions reduction in earnest. However, I would like to see the\n Commission able to bring forward or increase the target."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The Commission should be guided by science. I suspect that short lived gases do need to be reduced but perhaps not to zero. They\n\n do need to be taken seriously as methane is a more potent greenhouse gas."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I would support NZ reaching net negative carbon emissions in order to be able to sell carbon credits as an export."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But only to a more ambitious goal. It should not be vulnerable to weakening by lobby groups. Short term economic losses should be\n bourne to avoid larger long term losses."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I would also like to see a more ambitious short term budget to kick start the process."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "I do not support budgets being weakened. Governments should be able to respond to the science to increase targets as necessary.\n Climate change should not be a political football. Buy in by all parties should be saught, towards ambitious goals."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "It is already possible for the government to change the law when circumstances require. If the situation is so exceptional there is\n\n already a mechanism. There should not be a more easy mechanism."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I am concerned about empowering lobbyists to reduce goals. We need to be concerned about crossing environmental tipping points\n\nfrom which there is no return. I agree vulnerable populations should be protected and that the principles of the Treaty are very\nimportant to the Bill."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Accountability and implementation are crucial. It must not be possible for the Commission to be ignored or treated like a joke or made\nsecondary to other considerations."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Iwi involvement. Ideally, strong partnerships with agriculture that set up a culture of cooperation and progress, not lobbying to reduce\n\ntargets. Broader policies that impact vulnerable communities ; health, housing, benefits - and whether they are sufficient to cushion\nthe blow, especially to those already below the poverty line."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The ETS has seen carbon prices too low and failed to drive change. I believe an independent body is more likely to be able to make\n\nthe ETS effective."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Again I am concerned about lobbyists. I don’t think representatives from emmitting industries should be allowed positions of\nsignificant influence. However, their expertise is absolutely required to plan change."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But not to the detriment of its primary role in preventing climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I am a General Practitioner and support Ora Taiao’s position. I am personally prepared to forgo future gains in income and quality of\n\nlife, to pay more income tax and have my cost of living higher and ease of living reduced if it means my children will not be faced with\nthe crisis of climate change. I would much prefer strong immediate action with impacts on current GDP than reactive responses once\n\nthe crisis is here. In saying that, I am very concerned about the impacts of change on our most vulnerable citizens. I do not want to\nsee another 1984, nor GFC scale tidal wave of unemployment. The most vulnerable should be protected and supported. The Treaty\n\nmust be respected. I do not support simple consultation of Māori. They are the original and ongoing kaitiaki of NZ/Aotearoa and\nshould have a significant and, ideally, leading role within the Commission. Thank you for your consideration."
    }
  ]
}
